Guide to the Marilyn Symmes Collection of Art Exhibition Ephemera 1973-2019 (bulk 1990s-2019) PR 352
New-York Historical Society
Marilyn Symmes collection of art exhibition ephemera
1973-2019 (bulk 1990s-2019)
New-York Historical Society
Symmes, Marilyn F.
PR 352
15 Linear feet in 19 document boxes, 3 record cartons, and five oversize folders
The collection includes about 3,000 art gallery and museum announcements, posters, brochures, checklists, and other documents obtained by prints and drawings curator Marilyn F. Symmes, mostly from the 1990s-2019. Most of the material relates to modern and contemporary one-artist exhibitions, though two-artist and group exhibitions, including those with themed titles, are also represented. Most of the collection includes materials from New York City art galleries and museums, though institutions elsewhere in the United States and, to a lesser extent, in other countries are also represented.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes about 3,000 announcements, guides, brochures, checklists, artwork images, booklet catalogues, and posters from galleries, dealers and museums related to art exhibitions. These materials were either mailed to graphic arts curator Marilyn Symmes or obtained by her when visiting an exhibition. The bulk of the documents/exhibitions date from the 1990s to 2019, when Symmes was working at Cooper Hewitt in New York and later the Zimmerli at Rutgers.
Most of the collection contains documents related to modern and contemporary one-artist exhibitions. These exhibitions primarily included paintings, sculpture, video, photography, prints, drawings, and installations, with some architecture, design, and textiles. Many artists are represented by only one or two documents, while others include multiple documents. Both well-recognized names and less well known artists are found in the collection. The container list attempts to identify at the folder level those artists represented with more extensive or substantive content. Two-artist and group exhibitions, including those with themed titles, are also in the collection. Overall, as Symmes described the content when donating the collection to N-YHS, "The collection presents in microcosm a significant record of modern and contemporary artists whose work was exhibited during this period [1991-2019] primarily in New York City. This collection provides some insight into subjects, issues, materials, styles explored by artists as presented in these exhibitions—thereby reflecting a significant sampling of cultural and social concerns during this time period, as well as commercial interests of the American dealers."
Most of the collection includes materials from New York City art galleries and museums, though institutions elsewhere in the United States and, to a lesser extent, in other countries are also represented. Among the many galleries represented in the collection are: Alexandre, DC Moore, David Findlay Jr., Deitch Projects, Gemini G.E.L., Grey Art Gallery at N.Y.U., Hirschl & Adler, Gagosian, June Kelly, Mary Boone, Mary Ryan, Matthew Marks, Michael Werner, Marian Goodman, Marlborough, Michael Rosenfeld, Pace, Pace/Wildenstein, Peter Freeman, Sperone Westwater, Sonnabend, Susan Teller, UBU, and David Zwirner. Museums include, among others, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Museum of Modern Art (MoMA), Whitney, Guggenheim, New Museum, Noguchi, Brooklyn, MassMOCA, Philadelphia, Cooper-Hewitt, Yale, and Zimmerli at Rutgers.
Arrangement Note
The collection is organized in five series, as presented by the collector/donor:
Series I. Single Artist Exhibitions, 1973-2019 (bulk 1990s-2019)
Series II. Two Artists Exhibitions, 1994, 2000-2016
Series III. Multiple Artists Exhibitions, 1992-2016
Series IV. Architecture & New York City-related Exhibitions, 1991-2018
Series V. Holiday Greeting Cards, Invitations & Miscellaneous Posters, 2000-2018, undated
Biographical/Historical Note
Marilyn F. Symmes, a curator of prints and drawings, received her B.A. in art history from Stanford University and her M.A. in art history and museum practice from the University of Michigan. She began her curatorial career in the 1970s at the Smith College Museum of Art, later moving to the Detroit Institute of Arts and the Toledo Museum of Art.
In 1991, Symmes moved to New York City where she was Curator in charge of the Department of Drawings and Prints at Cooper-Hewitt, Smithsonian Design Museum until 2002. Symmes worked for the Smithsonian's Archives of American Art as the New York Area Collector from 2003-2004, and then as an independent curator until 2006. In 2006, Symmes was named Director of the Morse Research Center for Graphic Arts and Curator of Prints and Drawings at the Jane Voorhees Zimmerli Art Museum at Rutgers University. She held these positions until her retirement in 2015. She continues to remain involved with the art world by doing free-lance curatorial projects.
(The above note was based primarily on a biographical note provided by Marilyn Symmes to N-YHS curator Marilyn Kushner.)
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
Gift of Marilyn F. Symmes, 2016 and 2019.
Announcements; Brochures.; Ephemera.; Posters.; Art -- Exhibitions.; Art galleries, Commercial -- New York (State) -- New York.; Art museums; Arts publicity -- New York (State) -- New York.
- Series I. Single Artist Exhibitions, 1973-2019 (bulk 1990s-2019)
  Scope and Contents Note
  The series includes announcements, guides, brochures, checklists, artwork images, booklet catalogues, and posters from galleries, dealers and museums related to exhibitions centered on the work of one particular artist. The term "catalogue" is used loosely here and refers to a broad range of textual forms intended to provide some level of substantive insight into the content of an exhibition. By the donor's count, there are approximately 2,300 items in this series.
  The container list identifies some, though certainly not all or even most, of the artists represented in a particular folder of documents. Generally, artists were noted if there were several documents related to them or if the documents, even if only one was present, included substantive textual information, such as a checklist, description of artistic purpose, gallery layout, or biographical information. While acknowledging the subjective nature of the effort, an attempt was made to document within the container list where one could find brochure or booklet-type catalogues or other such documents concerning particular exhibitions. Researchers will no doubt find other useful documents within the folders, particularly high quality brochures emphasizing select artwork images or creatively designed gallery mailings, but not all artists and documents could be itemized in this finding aid within the constraints of processing resources.
  Arrangement Note
  The series is arranged alphabetically by artist surname, retaining the order as presented by the collector/donor. Entries in the container list that refer to "Set 2" are items added to the collection in 2019 by Marilyn Symmes that needed to be boxed apart from the original 2016 accession because of volume.
  Oversize items: The series includes many oversize items. Those that were originally folded and are only slightly oversize were typically left folded and boxed. Larger pieces were also left folded if it appeared that their design was such that the opening of the piece was integral to interpreting it or appreciating it as an object. Although the items are not especially fragile, care should be taken in unfolding and refolding them; please request assistance from the reference librarian as needed. Several oversize items that were more in the nature of posters were removed from the folders, flattened, and stored separately; all such items are noted individually at the end of the alphabetical container list under the label "oversize."
  - Aa-Al, 1994-2016 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes material from artists, among others, Marina Abramovic, Robert Adams, Yuji Agematsu, and Eric Aho.
  - Am-Ap, 2004-2013 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes material from artists, among others, Laurie Anderson, Benny Andrews, William Anthony, and Stephen Antonakos. Also includes a reflection by Laurie Anderson on her exhibition The Waters Reglitterized (2005). Includes catalogue Stephen Antonakos: Five Decades of Drawing from the Art Gallery at the Graduate Center of the City University of New York and a CD Stephen Antonakos: In his Studio.
  - Artschwager, Richard, 2003-2019 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ar-Az, 1995-2016 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes materials from artists, among others, Diane Arbus, Cory Arcangel, Siah Armajani, George Ault, and Milton Avery. Includes a Whitney catalogue Cory Arcangel: Pro Tools. Includes a selected chronology of Charles Arnoldi. Includes a folded, poster-sized invitation for Kutlug Ataman's Journey to the Moon (2009). Includes a list of works in Milton Avery's exhibition Milton Avery: Onrushing Waves.
  - Avadenka, Lynne, 2002-2013 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes exhibition invitations, book release postcards, and New Year's cards signed by artist.
  - Avedon, Richard, 2003-2018 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - A (Set 2), 1999-2019 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 1)
    Includes material from artists, among others, Magdalena Abakanowicz, Derrick Adams, Eric Aho, Eija-Liisa Ahtila, Benny Andrews, Ruth Asawa, and Milton Avery. Also includes a long biographical piece on the photographer, Dove Allouche. Aso includes an announ,cement and information regarding The Voyager's presentation of Laurie Anderson and the Nerve Bible Worldwide Tour. Includes a Hammer Museum brochure that has an excerpt of a conversation between the artist Anthony and guest curator, James Elaine, and a biography of Anthony.
  - Ba-Ban, 2002-2015 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes material from artists, among others, Francis Bacon, Trisha Baga, John Baldessari, and Balthus.
  - Bar, 1996-2016 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes material from artists, among others, Will Barnet, Hannelore Baron, and Jennifer Bartlett. Includes an invitation to Will Barnet's Gala Dinner to celebrate his 94th birthday and an invitation to celebrate Will Barnet at 100. Includes an invitation and press release for Jeannette Montgomery Barron on her portrait photograph exhibition. Includes a Jennifer Bartlett's postcard invitation with prices written on the back.
  - Barrada, Yto, 2018 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 2)
    A poster announcing Pace Gallery Exhibition of Yto Barrada, "How to do Nothing with Nobody All Alone by Yourself". Reverse side: "Ornament repertoire of all the Moroccan terra cotta tilework pieces".
  - Baselitz, Georg, 1999-2016 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes a brochure from the ESSL Collection with a short biography of the artist.
  - Bas-Ben, 1993-2016 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes material from artists, among others, Leonard Baskin, Jean-Michel Basquiat, David Bates, Lothar Baumgarten, Romare Bearden, and Sadie Benning. Includes also a catalogue from The Whitney on Sadie Benning's exhibition Play Pause.
  - Ber-Bl, 1999-2016 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes material from artists, among others, Joseph Beuys, Brett Bigbee, Oscar Bluemner, and Erwin Blumenfeld.
  - Boc-Boz, 1991-2015 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes material from artists, among others, Mel Bochner, Christian Boltanski, Lee Bontecou, Fernando Botero, Louise Bourgeois, and Dusty Boynton. Includes the Yale University Art Gallery catalogue and family guide for Mel Bochner: Thought Made Visible.
  - Bra-Bro, 1993-2016 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes material from artists, among others, Victor Brauner, Robert Broner, Marcel Broodthaers, Peter Brooke, Moe Brooker, James Brooks, Roger Brown, and Byron Browne. Includes also a Findlay Galleries catalogue, Peter Brooke: The Imagined and The Real.
  - Brown, Cecily, 2005-2014 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bu-By, 1995-2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes material from artists, among others, Charles Burchfield, Rudy Burckhardt, Chris Burden, and James Lee Byars.
  - B (Set 2) (2 folders), 1985-2019 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 3-4)
    Includes material from artists, among others, Jennifer Bartlett, David Bates, Romare Bearden, E.J. Bellocq, Huma Bhabha, Dara Birnbaum, Christian Boltanski, Marcel Broodthaers, Jude Broughan, Glenn Brown, and Richmond Burton. Also includes a catalogue of the eight silkscreened images by John Baldessari of his series, Madame Cezanne's Hairdos presented at Gemini G.E.L. in 2016. Also includes a brochure from The Museum of Contemporary Art San Diego on John Baldessari and The Print Retrospective from the Collections of Jordan D. Schnitzer and his Family Foundation. Includes a pamphlet advertising The Gehenna Press' book, "Grotesques"with etchings and writings by Baskin. Includes an announcement of a Mary Bauermeister exhibition, "live in peace or leave the galaxy", complete with a balloon to bring to the gallery for inflation. Includes a catalogue from Weil Gallery, Watson Fine Arts, Wheaton College of Allison Bianco Atlantic Time. Also includes a National Gallery of Art brochure on a 2011-2012 exhibition of works by Mel Bochner. Includes a MOMA brochure on a 1995 exhibition of The Prints of Louise Bourgeois. Includes an announcement of a 2017 exhibition of works by Katherine Bradford with an excerpt from an article about the artist by Chris Martin. Also includes a brochure from the Highpoint Center for Printmaking on an exhibition of New Prints by Julie Buffalohead with her biography.
  - Ca-Cav, 1993-2015 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
    Material from artists, including, among others, Paul Cadmus, John Cage, Alexander Calder, Sophie Calle, Cornell Capa, Anthony Caro, Mary Cassatt, James Castle, and Maurizio Cattelan. Also includes a 2004 Edmond Casarella brochure from the Susan Teller Gallery with a price list.
  - Ce-Clo, 1995-2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4)
    Material from artists, including, among others, Marc Chagall, John Chamberlain, Dale Chihuly, Francesco Clemente, and Chuck Close.
  - Co-Coy, 1995-2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 5)
    Materials from artists, including, among others, Sue Coe, Dan Colen, James Coleman, James Cornell, Luc Courchesne, and Petah Coyne. Includes prospectus for The Ballad of Lemon and Crow by Glenn Todd, illustrated by Bruce Connor and anonymous artists.
  - Cr-Cy, 1995-2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 6)
    Materials from artists, including, among others, Gregory Crewdson, John Cross, Merce Cunningham, and John Currin. Also includes a 1999 Queens College Art Center exhibition catalogue for John Crawford Sculpture, a 1995 Laurence Miller Gallery catalogue for Ralston Crawford Abstracting the Vernacular, and a 2003 Des Moines Art Center exhibition catalogue for John Currin Works on Paper.
  - C (Set 2), 1986-2019 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 5)
    Includes material from artists, among others, Alexander Calder, Ernst Caramelle, Elizabeth Catlett, Paul Chan, Barbara Chase-Riboud, Chuang Che, Chuck Close, Elaine Lustig Cohen, James Coleman, Mary Corse, and Tony Cragg. Also includes a brochure from the Penland Gallery on an exhibition, "Parched/Inverted Landscapes" by Susan Goethel Campbell with a biography of the artist. Includes a The Met Breuer brochure on "Vija Celmins: To Fix the Image in Memory". Includes a Elaine L. Jacob Gallery catalogue on Enrique Chagoya with a paper insert that includes his biography. Also includes two brochures from the Queens Museum from the Patty Chang exhibition, "The Wandering Lake 2009-2017". Includes a brochure advertising "X" by Sue Coe, published by Raw Books & Graphics. Also includes "Poetry", a Gagosian Gallery catalogue of works by Dan Colen. Includes a Beach Museum of Art at Kansas State University brochure on the John Steuart Curry, The Way of the Modern Adventurers Exhibition.
  - Da-DeK, 1996-2016 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
    Materials from artists, including, among others, Hanne Darboven, James Daugherty, Enrico David, Bruce Davidson, and Edgar Degas. Also includes a 2005 Boston Athenaeum exhibition catalogue for Power Line: The Art of Leo Dee.
  - De Kooning, Willem and Elaine, 1994-2013 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
    Includes a brochure from Washburn for 1994 exhibition Elaine de Kooning: Artists and Writers; other documents relate to Willem only. Includes a 1996 Whitney Museum brochure "Collection in Context: Willem de Kooning's Door Cycle" and a 2006 Matthew Marks Gallery checklist for Willem's exhibition Sketchbook.
  - Del-Die, 1996-2016 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
    Materials from artists, including, among others, thomas Demand, Walter De Maria, Claudia DeMonte, Philip-Lorca diCorcia, and Richard Diebenkorn. Also includes a Whitney Museum 1996 exhibition catalogue for Jane Dickson Paradise Alley.
  - Dij-Doi, 2003-2016 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
    Materials from artists, including, among others, Jim Dine, Mark Dion installation The Octagon Room and Lois Dodd.
  - Don-Dy, 2003-2015 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5)
    Materials from artists, including, among others, Tara Donovan, Arthur Dove, David Driskell, Jean Dubuffet, and Carroll Dunham.
  - D (Set 2), 1991-2019 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 6)
    Includes material from artists, among others, Joyce Melander-Dayton, Tacita Dean, Claudia DeMonte, Robert DeNiro, Sr., Jan Dibbets, Lesley Dill, Kim Dingle, Lois Dodd, Tara Donovan, Jim Dow, Sally Hazelet Drummond, and Valerie Duncan. Also includes a DIA brochure on the Hanne Darboven exhibition, "Kulturgeschichte 1880-1983, 1980-83", with a biography of the artist. Includes a Whitney brochure and postcard on the E.V. Day: G-Force exhibition. Includes a NYU Grey Art Gallery brochure on the exhibition, "Diebenkorn in New Mexico". Also includes a Morgan Library brochure on the temporary installation of 3 scultures by Mark di Suvero at the Morgan. Includes a Smith College Museum of Art brochure on the installation, "Portals, Pivots, and Perspectives: An Installation by Patrick Dougherty". Also includes a Zabriskie Gallery brochure on a Marcel Duchamp exhibition, "Marcel Duchamp on Display: Optics, Exhibition Installations, Portable Museums".
  - Eb-Ei, 1993-2016 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 6)
    Materials from artists, including, among others, Melvin Edwards and William Eggleston.
  - El-Ev, 2001-2014 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
    Materials from artists, including, among others, Olafur Eliasson and Lalla Essaydi.
  - E (Set 2), 2001-2014 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 7)
    Includes material from artists, Melvin Edwards and Nicole Eisenman. Includes a brochure from the Zimmerli Art Museum at Rutgers University, "Melvin Edwards, Five Decades", tucked into the brochure is a guide to Melvin Edwards Public Sculpture in New Jersey. Also includes a UPenn ICA brochure on the "Dear Nemesis, Nicole Eisenman 1993-2013" exhibition with a biography of the artist.
  - Fa-Fin, 1999-2016 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
    Materials from artists, including, among others, Shepard Fairey, Zeng Fanzhi, Tony Feher, Teresita Fernandez. Also includes a David Findlay Jr. Gallery 2012 catalogue for John Ferren Works from the 1950s-1960s.
  - Fis-Fox, 1991-2016 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
    Includes materials from artists, including, among others, Urs Fischer and Dan Flavin. Also includes a 2001 Durham Press catalogue Roland Fischer: Facades on Paper and a 2014 David Findlay Jr. Gallery checklist for Gordon Onslow Ford Space Elements.
  - Fra-Fre, 1973-2015 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
    Includes materials from artists, including, among others, Robert Frank, Helen Frankenthaler, Norbert Freese, and Jane Freilicher.
  - Fri-Fus, 1995-2016 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
    Includes materials from artists, including, among others, Lee Friedlander, Yang Fudong, and Buckminster Fuller. Also includes a Marian Goodman Gallery 2012 brochure with interview extracts with Yang Fudong.
  - F (Set 2), 1991-2019 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 8)
    Includes material from artists, among others, Claire Falkenstein, Robert Filliou, Janet Fish, Llyn Foulkes, Mary Frank, Helen Frankenthaler, Suzan Frecon, and Lee Friedlander. Also includes a brochure from The Menil Collection on the Dan Flavin Installation at Richmond Hall.
  - Ga-Gh, 1995-2015 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    Includes materials from artists, including, among others, Ellen Gallagher, Frank Gehry, and Juan Genoves. Also includes a Betty Cuningham Gallery 2006 catalogue for Charles Garabedian.
  - Gia-Gol, 1992-2015 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
    Includes materials from artists, including, among others, Alberto Giacometti, Gilbert & George, Allen Ginsberg, Alexander Girard, and Andy Goldsworthy.
  - Gon-Gra, 1994-2015 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1)
    Includes materials from artists, including, among others, chris Gonyea, Brenda Goodman, Douglas Gordon, Arshile Gorky, Dan Graham, and Paul Graham.
  - Gre-Gro, 1993-2016 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 2)
    Includes materials from artists, including, among others, Red Grooms and Mark Grotjahn. Also includes a David Findlay Jr. Gallery 2013 catalogue for John Grillo: Works from the 1940s, 1950s, and 1960s.
  - Gu-Gut, 1997-2012 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 3)
    Includes materials from artists, including, among others, Andreas Gursky and Philip Guston. Also includes a 2002 announcement for a publication of Sandrine Guerin's Folio 1 with photographs of the four etchings to be included in the folio. Includes a 1997 walking tour guide "The Old World Builds New York: Guastavino Construction in Manhattan, 1886-1954," produced by the Avery Library at Columbia University
  - G (Set 2), 1980's-2019 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 9)
    Includes material from artists, among others, John Ganis, Adrian Ghenie, Bruce Gilden, John Giorno, Joseph Glasco, Leon Golub, John Graham, Rodney Graham, John Grillo, Wang Guangle, and Andreas Gursky. Also includes an information sheet from the ICA in Philadelphia on its exhibition, "Rudi Gernreich: Fashion Will Never Go Out of Fashion." Also includes a card from the June Kelly Gallery on the exhibition, "Joan Giordano: Woven in Time, Constructions & Mixed Media" with an explanation of the artist's work. Includes a Barnes Foundation brochure on the William Glackens exhibition. Also includes a catalogue from the exhibition, "Michael Goldberg: End to End, The 1950's & 2000s." Also includes a Michael Rosenfeld Gallery Frieze Masters: Spotlight on "Nancy Grossman, The 1960's."
  - Haa-Han, 1999-2016 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 4)
    Includes materials from artists, including, among others, Zaha Hadid, Richard Hamilton, and Stephen Hannock. Also includes opening invitations and several exhibition catalogues /checklists for Jane Hammond.
  - Har-Hay, 1993-2016 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 5)
    Includes material from artists, including, among others, Keith Haring, Marsden Hartley, Joseph Havel, and Tim Hawkinson. Also includes Museum of Modern Art 2003 exhibition catalogue for Here is Elsewhere, Mona Hatoum's contribution to MoMA's Artist's Choice series.
  - He-Hir, 1992-2016 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 6)
    Includes materials for artists, including, among others, Al Held, Jean Helion, Auguste Herbin, Eva Hesse, and Damien Hirst. Also includes a Dieu Donne Papermill 2005 exhibition catalogue for Arturo Herrera How to drown while looking at a piece of paper.
  - Ho-Hol, 2001-2016 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1)
    Includes material for artsists, including, among others, David Hockney, Howard Hodgkin, Candida Hofer, Marietta Hoferer, and Jenny Holzer. Also includes a fundraising solicitation for art Matters, Inc, with enclosed Jenny Holzer Truism Stamps.
  - Hon-Hy, 1994-2015 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 2)